Hello and welcome to the
first video with It's Dr.
Dan and what we're going to
be doing is we're going to be
learning all about chemistry.
And when, why, why exactly are we here?
What is the point of taking a
chemistry class other than what
we got to do as a prerequisite?
Well, chemistry is one of those
courses that helps to bring
together essentially everything
that you're learning in college.
Whether it's biology or learning about
health science courses, it helps us be
able to describe the world around you.
It helps you be able to
observe things, right?
If you want to be a health care provider,
And you are taking care of a patient.
You are making observations
about their health conditions.
You're writing down numbers.
You are taking note of how their
pain levels, you are writing a lot
of things down so that doctors and
the team members in the hospital
know how to save an individual.
Uh, if you are someone that's maybe
working in, let's say, the agricultural
industry, and you want to get the
highest possible crop yield, you're
going to be possibly measuring soil
pHs, looking at how the trees and the,
and the different groves are behaving.
You need to take measurements, need to
actually observe those different changes.
They are all around us as we are, are
looking at these different things.
Now, when we are trying to understand
the whole idea of measurement.
and observation.
There, there is a lot that can
realistically go into this.
It is, it can be really, really
complicated and it can get a
little scary too along the way.
So let's go into it.
Let's try to figure out exactly what is
chemistry, what are, why are we trying
to torture ourselves with this class?
What are we trying to learn along the way?
Now, when it comes to chemistry, The first
thing is understanding, well, what is it?
What exactly are we doing?
Right?
We always say like, oh,
they have chemistry.
Well, what does that mean?
Well, chemistry was defined, has
been defined for ages now, but one
of the things that that definition
behind it is always kind of.
Then redefine, redefine, but there's
always been one single constant that's
always existed, and that is change.
There's always change.
And that is what chemistry is all
about, is trying to figure out,
well, what exactly is changing?
So, if I were to just look at, let's say,
this really, this car that I have here
on this slide, and I were to ask you,
Well, what can you observe about this car?
Well, you can say like,
well, it's a really nice car.
It's a sports car.
It's red.
It's, it's very nice metal.
But if you let this thing, let's say it
sits outside for 30 years, 40 years and
all the elements and raining conditions
near maybe a coastline where there's
salt in the air, what could happen to it?
Well, it could turn into this, right?
It could turn into an old rust bucket.
Now it's still a sports car.
It's still Mustang.
It's still can do probably zero to
60 with a lot of love and support,
but it does not look the same.
There has been change
that has occurred here.
Well, how can you define that change?
How can you, what can you say about it?
Well, before, right, we could
say the car was really red.
It was very shiny.
Now it's kind of like brown.
It's orange.
There's like some white part tents here.
It's all falling apart.
Um, you know, it's not completely
the car that you knew about before.
So when we are talking about chemistry,
what we're trying to see is here, uh, is
that it allows us to really understand
how and why Matt matter is changing.
Now, what is matter?
What is the matter?
Matter is essentially anything
that has a mass and it has a
volume and it's something that
is, that exists around you, right?
Everything around you has matter,
whether it's maybe, let's say
like my notes or maybe like my
coffee cup or, uh, this pencil.
I'm just grabbing things around me, right?
All these things.
are made of matter.
Now, what we're trying to do is figure
out is how and why can they possibly
change and it's all around you.
This is one of the reasons why this
is such an important course because
it's, it's an everyday life, right?
We see it everywhere.
Now, when it comes to like some
examples, really, and I'll be showing
these examples again later in the
semester is that you can see it.
Everywhere.
Whether it's, let's say, the trees around
you, trying to give you oxygen in order
to live and to exist, photosynthesis
is taking the CO2 out of the air and
creating energy for itself, and it's
creating natural sugars, um, in the
process in order to live, and also makes
O2, which is necessary for us to live.
If you're someone that loves to eat,
right, we all eat every single day,
that digestion process is hundreds of
reactions that are occurring one after
another, after another with enzymes
in different metabolic pathways to
help us really be able to see how can
your body break something down, right?
If you eat this giant, let's say, piece
of bread or this big steak, right, you
sure you're breaking down your teeth, but.
That's only the beginning.
It has to go through the
entire digestive tract, right?
So if you're taking chemistry,
eventually you'll take anatomy
and physiology as well.
And this is the foundation to
understanding that process.
For a lot of us as well, right?
If we just went through a pandemic and
we had a lot, we were, I mean, you still
should you're told to wash your hands
and wear masks and do all these things,
washing your hands, putting soap on your
hands will destroy bacterial cell walls.
So that way they can't easily reproduce.
Right?
So it's something that
helps stop that process.
If you're over the age of 21
and you like beer and wine,
right, that is chemistry, right?
Yeast is making alcohol and it's
something that is enjoyed by
millions of people around the world.
Same thing if you're a
baker or a cooker, right?
If you do any of those things, um, or
chef, not cooker, and you do any of those
things, all those are chemical reactions.
It's everywhere, right?
You probably have made something
the past 48 hours, right?
In your kitchen.
That was chemistry.
You are already on your first steps.
If you are currently looking at your
cell phone or your laptop to watch
this video or your phone, the batteries
in it, the screen that you have,
think of the, what is an led, right?
That is a light emitting diode, which
is essentially made of different
chemicals that are all different,
that's different, that are in different
combinations to help you see me right now.
Same with your batteries, right?
That charge is electrons
being transferred.
They're everywhere.
When it comes to matter, we
are observing these things.
It takes up many different
forms, as I said.
So, what are some of those forms?
Well, let's look at what can you see?
What do you observe?
How can you measure it?
Ask those questions for yourself,
especially as you're going through lab.
You want to be able to see what is
it that you are looking at here.
So, if I look at the first one, right,
you can see this, uh, pot of water here.
It's boiling, right?
We can see the fire that's hot.
But what exactly are we seeing
on The atomic scale, right?
We want to start thinking
it's small, right?
Chemistry is all about the atoms,
and that's what we're going to
be talking about in the future.
So if you kind of zoom in on that water,
and let's say if I want to look at the
really tiny picture of that, well, these
are made of water molecules, right?
Little atoms that are all bound together.
If I look at a balloon and I look
at the one next to it, right, you
can see that this is a helium atoms
that are inside of it that are so far
apart that it's caught and they're so
light and not that not dense at all.
That's causing the
balloon to float, right?
It's made of different atoms that
are have different compositions.
When it comes to matter, there's different
properties behind all of them, right?
If you think of water, you can drink it.
You can, it has a certain,
maybe kind of taste to it.
It's a liquid at a room temperature.
It can, if it gets cold
enough, it turns into a solid.
If it gets too hot, it turns into steam.
And, It's made of all these
things called particles, right?
So particles are anything that's a really
tiny Atomic microscopic particle and
this is what makes up all the matter
There are organized in a very specific
way to make up all these things now So
this is what matters composed of and
we're gonna be Referring to a lot of the
chemistry that we're gonna look at in
the next few weeks or on this channel
is from the particle standpoint Right.
So what, how exactly can we understand
that now when it comes to these different
particles, how exactly are they organized?
Well, it's all from the periodic
table, which I like to refer to
it as the chemist alphabet, right?
When you first learn how to read
and write, you learn the alphabet.
You learned how all these different
orders of letters can produce.
All kinds of interesting combinations
of words that you speak on a regular
basis, or you text on a regular basis,
or you send in a DM on a regular basis.
It's the same idea.
You have this alphabet here that
you're trying to understand.
And one of the things about it is
they want to start kind of memorizing
it, especially if you're going to be
taking a chemistry course, taking a
lot of science courses, this table
is going to be referred to a lot.
And the big reason why it's good, why
is it so referred to is being that,
like I said, matter has properties.
And this table organizes all
of the properties within it.
So it helps us be able to understand
basic idea of, okay, there's properties.
Now how is that organized?
Well, if you look at the columns
and then look at the first one,
these are called the alkali metals.
And I recommend knowing the
names of the major areas.
These are very reactive.
Essentially, if you throw any of these in
water, um, they will immediately explode.
Let's try to take a look
at how that would work.
So one thing that you'll notice, the
alkali metals are very, very reactive.
So this one's lithium, and as you can
see, this professor is adding it to water.
You can see it's bubbling,
it's releasing hydrogen gas.
They added an indicator that changes
the water color, so it's showing
how it's going to produce an acid.
This is sodium, so going down the
periodic table, this one's even more
reactive, you see it bubbling even
more and more and more, and then
you're going to see it explodes, how
much it actually will show from this.
Then going down to potassium, so
that's lithium, sodium, now potassium.
This is going to be more reactive,
it instantly catches on fire,
it starts sparking, exploding.
You can see how reactive these
chemicals are and as they are reacting,
they get even more and more violent.
And if you kept going down
the periodic table, you'll
see it like it's even crazier.
So this is potassium in slow motion
and you can see how it's sparking, it's
exploding, it's very, very violent.
And this is being done in a
classroom at a university.
So that was really cool to see, right?
Alkaline metals are very, very reactive.
Taking a little bit from
some other people, right?
They are reactive.
Now, if you look at alkaline earth
metals, this is what we see in fireworks
and displays and all the different
colors that we can see as well.
As you can see, all the different
properties that are here are
all extremely different, right?
And they're right next to
each other in the PR table.
Every single element has
its own unique properties.
Now, when it comes to the other ones,
which are the pnictogens, the chalcogens,
and the halogens, a little bit of a tongue
twister, you don't have to be perfect
in knowing those first two there, but
the halogens, as you know, these are
all very, very different gases, right?
The ones on the left, all
metals, they're all solids.
They're all, have different properties,
so alkali metals are very reactive.
Alkaline, not so reactive
unless you put a flame to it.
The other ones are all gases.
A lot of them are found
within our atmosphere.
Then eventually the
halogens are super reactive.
And the last one is the noble gases.
These are always, I always say,
are dignified and above the rest.
And they don't quite interact as much.
Right, we have all these different things.
They're organized.
They all have different properties.
That's the important thing.
Now that we realize that, how, this
is one thing that we need to make
sure we start to understand, and to
start memorizing as we move forward.
Because we need to be able to
observe the universe around us, we
need to be able to understand it.
Start memorizing it, but the
thing is, depending on your chem
class, in my course, you don't
have to memorize the whole thing.
I tell everybody, the first 20
elements is a good starting point.
You want to be able to,
essentially, memorize.
The symbols and then their names, put
them on flashcards, help you remember
them because they are the common ones.
The first 20, a lot of them are the
essential minerals that are found within
the human body to help keep us alive.
If you're a health scientist, you
will commonly refer to a lot of them.
Let's say for example, potassium K.
A lot of times some people are
potassium deficient and you need
to be able to tell them that.
So right, it's going to be written
by the letter K to represent that.
Calcium is one of the things that you,
if you drink milk, you use calcium to
make strong bones, as I say, it's a
very important mineral within the body.
So a lot of these are common, right?
You see them all around you to
memorize the first 20, put them
on flashcards and start learning.
This has been Dr.
Dan and we're going to be,
I'll see you in the next video.
Thank you so much for stopping
by and I'll see you all later.
Bye now.